A Guide to the Christine Hoepfner Collection on the Shenandoah National Park, 1911 - 2000: SC 0170
Special Collections, Carrier Library, James Madison University
Christine Hoepfner Collection on the Shenandoah National Park,
1911-2000
Special Collections, James Madison University
Hoepfner, Christine, (-2018)
SC 0170
.6 cubic feet; 2 boxes
Contains photocopies of letters, reports, and news stories, mostly from the National Archives and the Shenandoah National Park Archives, which deal with the formation and early administration of Shenandoah National Park in Virginia.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research. Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection. Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the James Madison University Special Collections Library to use this collection.
Acquisition Information
Donated by Christine Hoepfner in 2002
Bio/Historical Note
Christine Hoepfner began working for Shenandoah National Park as a historian and archaeologist in 1992. While out in the field one day she met an elderly man who told her for the first time about the removal of mountain families. At the time, Hoepfner was also working on a Ph.D. dissertation about the creation of Shenandoah National Park for the University of Pennsylvania. Later, she served as president of The Children of Shenandoah, a group of descendants of the families removed, formed in 1994 by Lisa Custalow to lobby for more complete and accurate historical displays and videos in Park visitor centers. Hoepfner moved away from the area in 2002.
Scope and Content
This collection contains photocopies of of letters, reports, memos, land records and other documents from the National Archives and Shenandoah National Park archives concerning the formation and early administration of Shenandoah National Park. The condemnation of private land and removal of approximately 500 families from the Park in the 1930s, the attempts of those families to deal with the government, and the response of the public and of governmental agencies to the removal, form the focus of the collection. Also included are newspaper articles about the removal, and programs and newsletters documenting the later establishment of a group of descendents of the removed families, The Children of Shenandoah.
Series 1, Letters/Correspondence, 1925-1999, consists of 9 folders, which contain letters and correspondence between government officials/members of the Department of the Interior and residents of the area of the proposed Shenandoah National Park and other private citizens. Also contains job applications and work requests for the Department of the Interior, along with letters to President Franklin D. Roosevelt, messages from John D. Rockefeller Jr. and various reports and legal documents pertaining to permits, land ownership and resettlement efforts.
Series 2, Publications, 1911-1990, consists of 4 folders which contain press releases and letters concerning news stories from the Department of the Interior, various newspaper articles, and dissertations and publications.
Series 3, Children of Shenandoah, 1981-2000, consists of 1 folder containing letters, program announcements, and other items pertinent to the establishment and work of the group, Children of Shenandoah.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged topically into three series.
Series 1. Letters/Correspondence, 1925-1999
Series 2. Publications, 1911-1990
Series 3. Children of Shenandoah, 1981-2000
Index Terms
Subjects:
Shenandoah National Park (Va.) -- History; Children of Shenandoah (Organization); Shenandoah National Park (Va.); Mountain people -- Virginia -- Shenandoah National Park -- Social life and customs; Mountain life -- Virginia -- Shenandoah National Park -- History; Mountain people -- Blue Ridge Mountains -- Social life and customs; National parks and reserves -- Appalachian Region, Southern -- History; Recreation areas -- Virginia -- Shenandoah National Park -- History; Shenandoah River Valley (Va. and W. Va.) -- History
- Series 1: Letters/Correspondence, 1925-1999, undated
  - Department of Interior with Residents (A-M), 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Content
    Correspondence between residents within the proposed boundaries of Shenandoah National Park and officials of the Department of the Interior. Arranged alphabetically by name of resident.
  - Depart of Interior with Residents (M-Z), 1930-1938 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Private citizens with government agencies, 1925-1939 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Correspondence between private citizens and various governmental agencies concerning artifacts for a museum. Includes a 1925 "Donor's Certificate." Arranged chronologically.
  - Memos, Letters from John D. Rockefeller, 1926-1934 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Memos and letters mostly among state and federal officials on administrative aspects of Shenandoah National Park, but also includes letters on funding from John D. Rockefeller, Jr.
  - Memos, Letters from John D., Rockefeller, 1935-1948, undated (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Job Applications/Work Requests, 1933-1941 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Job applications and work requests to the Department of the Interior.
  - Letters to Franklin Delano Roosevelt, 1933-1937, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
    Letters to President Franklin D. Roosevelt concerning removal of mountain people.
  - Land Records, 1927-1952, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Contains letters, reports, and legal documents concerning ownership of land, permits, and resettlement efforts.
  - Land plats, 1927-1999, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
    Contains ownership plats for some tracts within the Park including Cave Cemetery, and lists of map sources.
- Series 2: Publications, 1911-2000, undated
  - Deptartment of Interior Press Releases/Letters, 1928-1996 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Press releases and letters concerning news stories from the Department of the Interior.
  - Newspaper Articles, 1911-1949 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Newspaper Articles, 1971-1999 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Dissertations and Publications, 1991, undated (Box 2, Folder 4)
    Includes excerpts from or citations to six dissertations.
- Series 3: Children of Shenandoah, 1981-2000
  - Letters, program announcements, etc., 1981-2000 (Box 2, Folder 5)
    Letters, program announcements, and other items pertinent to the establishment and work of the group, Children of Shenandoah.